<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The testimonie of a true fayth conteyned in a short catechisme necessary to all families, for the more knowledge of God, and better bryngyng  vp of chyldren in his fayth and feare. Gathered and written for the benefite of Gods well disposed children, By C.S. Preacher.</title>
            <author>Shutte, Christopher, d. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15228</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15228)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1585:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The testimonie of a true fayth conteyned in a short catechisme necessary to all families, for the more knowledge of God, and better bryngyng  vp of chyldren in his fayth and feare. Gathered and written for the benefite of Gods well disposed children, By C.S. Preacher.</title>
                  <author>Shutte, Christopher, d. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Nygh vnto the three Cranes in the Vintree by Thomas Dawson, and Thomas Gardyner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Do. 1577. March 10.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.S. = Christpher Shutte.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology --  Miscellanea --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TESTIMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a true Fayth: <hi>Conteyned in a ſhorte</hi> Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, neceſſary to all Families, <hi>for the more knowledge of God,</hi> and better bryngyng vp of <hi>Chyldren in his fayth and feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gathered and written for the benefite</hi> of Gods well diſpoſed children, <hi>by C. S. Preacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London,</hi> nygh vnto the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas <hi>Dawſon, and Thomas Gardyner. Anno Do. 1577.</hi> March. 10.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The Testimonie</hi> of a true fayth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the duetie of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian alwayes to be readye<note n="a." place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15</note> to render an account of his fayth, to the ende it may appeare, that he is not<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 10.32 Rom. 10.10</note> aſhamed of Chriſt &amp; his Doctrine. Let me therefore heare what thou canſt ſaye of the principall poynts of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be three ſpeciall parts therof. the firſt is<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 17.3 2. Cor. 13.5</note> to know God and my ſelfe: the ſecond is,<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 5.24</note> the meanes wherby my ſaluation is wrought: the third,<note n="c." place="margin">Matth. 6.9 and. 26.26</note> what helpes God doth further mee withall vnto lyfe euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſayſt thou of the knowledge of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame is of two ſortes: the one is vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, and knowen<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 1.19 Pſalm. 19.1</note> by the creation of heauen and earth, wherin God offereth him ſelfe to be ſeene and knowen of me, as the onely fountayne of all goodneſſe, who alone<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 6.13</note> ought to be worſhipped. For his<note n="c." place="margin">Geneſ. 1.1 Act. 17.24</note> eternitie appereth in the making of the world, his<note n="d." place="margin">Pſalm. 36</note> goodnes in preſeruing the ſame, his<note n="e." place="margin">Pſalm. 107 Act. 17.28 Pſal. 115.3</note> prouidence in the tokens whiche are ſeene
<pb facs="tcp:15228:3"/> and felt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.3.</note> wherby what pleaſeth his godly will commeth to paſſe, and not by blynd fortune: his<note n="f." place="margin">Pſal. 104.24</note> wiſedome in ordering of the things created: hys<note n="g." place="margin">Rom. 2.7.8.9.10.</note> ryghtuouſneſſe in deliuering the godly, &amp; puniſhing the wicked: hys<note n="h." place="margin">Ezec. 18.32</note> mercy in paciently forbearing ſynners, and calling them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. So that what may be knowen of God, is manyfeſt in the things created, which vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall knowledge taketh away<note n="i." place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> al excuſe from the vngodly, whiche worſhyp not God aryght: but to me it is a<note n="k." place="margin">Pſal. 19.1.</note> ready way to bring me to the true worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>The other knowledge is ſpecial, &amp; onely proper<note n="l." place="margin">Iohn. 17.3 Iere. 31.34</note> to the elect, wherby, through faith poured in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hart by the holy ghoſt, I am aſſured that my ſaluation is wrought by Chriſt the Sonne of God, by whome<note n="m." place="margin">Ro. 8.16</note> I am made the childe of God thorow grace, and heyre with Chriſt of his kingdome, which knowledge onely commeth of<note n="n." place="margin">Luk. 10.21</note> grace, and ſo is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me, but it is reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the wicked, becauſe of their<note n="o." place="margin">Mat. 13.14</note> ſinne and hardnes of hart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſayſt thou of the knowledge of thy ſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By creation I was made in Adam, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the<note n="a." place="margin">Geneſ. 2.27 Epheſ. 4.24</note> Image of God (I meane not any bodily ſhape, for God is a<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 4.24</note> ſpirit, and without
<pb facs="tcp:15228:3"/> body (in true rightuouſnes &amp; holynes, that is to ſay, in al perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and happines of nature, both in ryght iudgement, reaſon, wyll, &amp; ſtrength. In which happy ſtate, if Adam had continued, both I and al his poſteritie had bene bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How diddeſt thou fall from this grace?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My fall appeareth, in that<note n="a." place="margin">Gene. 3. toto Rom. 5.12.13</note> Adam who had thys bleſſing for me, thorow the intiſement of the ſerpent brake the commaundement of God, in eating of the forbidden fruite, and by the ſame depriued him ſelfe of his former happynes, and brought ſynne, death, hel, the wrath of God, and all kynde of miſeries into the world, as iuſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for his deſerts. In which his ſinful act, his pride, diſobedience, lacke of fayth, vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to his creatour, lyght credit to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll appeared. In which offence, both I and all his ofſpring are wrapped, in as much as in hym we all haue ſynned, for he had the bleſſing geuen, to keepe or looſe, for hym and his. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I, and al others deſcending of hym, by him, and in hym, haue fallen from grace, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected wyth hys corruptions,<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 51.5</note> conceyued in ſin, borne in eniquitie, and<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3 Rom. 3.2</note> by nature the children of wrath, and vtterly vndone, without the grace and mercy of God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How art thou reſtored to grace agayne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My reſtauration commeth thorow<note n="a." place="margin">Titus. 3.10 Epheſ. 2.4</note> the free mercy and fauour of God, who after this my fall in Adam, rayſed both hym and me vp again with the comfortable<note n="b." place="margin">Geneſ. 3.15 &amp;. 12.2. &amp; 22.18</note> promiſe of a Saueour, who by his<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.25 Coloſ. 1.22 2. Cor. 5.21</note> death ſhoulde pacifie the wrath of God, and bring me into his fauour agayne:<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 5.19</note> by whoſe obedience I am made ryghtuous: which my regeneration commeth thus to me, whyleſt<note n="e." place="margin">Matth. 3.2 Luk. 24.47</note> by the preaching of the Lawe I am brought to the feeling of my ſyns, and rayſed vp with the comfortable promiſes of the Goſpell, receyued by fayth.<note n="f." place="margin">Act. 15.9 1. Cor. 3.16</note> My hart is lightned, purifyed, and gouerned by the holy Ghoſt:<note n="g." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24</note> my wil and mind reformed, and the image of God renued agayne in me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewe me what be the meanes wherby thy ſaluation is wrought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ordinary meanes commonly are two, that is to ſay,<note n="a." place="margin">Luk. 24.47 Rom. 10.17</note> the word of God, and fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the word of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is thoſe Canonicall ſcriptures<note n="a." place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16</note> written
<pb facs="tcp:15228:4"/> by the ſpirit of God,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and commended to man both in the olde and in the new Teſtament, wherin are conteyned<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 4.2 &amp; 12.32 Galat. 1.8 Luk. 16.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> all things neceſſary to ſaluation, according to the which, the Lord will haue all his religion meaſured, without eyther addyng or dimiſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How canſt thou know the true Religion, in ſo many opinions of the ſame, as be in the world?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fyrſt, I trye the religion taught me<note n="a." place="margin">Act. 17.11 Iohn. 5.39</note> by the word of God, and by his ſpirit geuen me to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſame. Secondly,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> I know thys ſpirit to be a ryght ſpirit, becauſe it confeſſeth Chriſt to be come in the fleſhe, that is to ſay, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth the whole worke of my ſaluation to him, and to no other thing. Thyrdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.31</note> I expound one place of Scripture, as it is not contrarye to another. And thus I trye the truth,<note n="d." place="margin">Ioh. 12.48</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the worde of God to iudge and determine what I ought to folowe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is the worde of God deuided?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into the<note n="a." place="margin">Matth. 3.2 Luk. 24.47</note> Law and Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the Lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:5"/>
            <p>It is the ten commaundementes of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of euery one<note n="a." place="margin">Deut. 27.26</note> moſt pure, perfect, and perpetuall obedience,<note n="b." place="margin">Leuit. 18.5 Rom. 10.5 Math. 19.17</note> promiſyng ſaluation to them which fulfill the ſame, threatning death and damnation to the tranſgeſſours thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rehearſe the ſame to me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Exod. 20</note> Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Image, nor the likenes of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the waters vnder he earth: thou ſhalt not bowe down to them nor worſhip them, for I the Lord thy God am a ielous god, viſiting the iniquities of the fathers vpon the children vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhewe mercy to thouſandes, in them that loue me and keepe my commaundements.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vayne, for the Lord will not holde him giltles that taketh his name in vayne.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Remember that thou keepe holy the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both daye, ſixe dayes ſhalt thou labour and do all that thou haſt to doo, but the ſeuenth day is the Sabboth of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt doo no manner of worke, thou, nor thy ſonne, nor thy daughter, thy man ſeruaunt, and thy mayde
<pb facs="tcp:15228:5"/> ſeruaunt, thy cattel, and ſtraunger within thy gates: for in ſixe dayes the Lord made heauen and earth, the ſea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeuenth day, wherefore the Lord bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſeuenth day, and hallowed it.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Honour thy father and thy mother, that thy dayes may bee long in the land which the Lord thy God geueth thee.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Thou ſhalt not kill.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit adultry.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes againſt thy neighbour.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Thou ſhalt not couet thy neyghbours houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours wife, nor his ſeruaunt, nor his maid, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſayſt thou of the firſt commaundement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord therin requireth<note n="a." place="margin">1. Sa. 15.22 Deut. 10.12</note> true obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his word, the feare &amp; loue of his name,<note n="b." place="margin">Ioh. 3.15.16</note> a ſure faith &amp; truſt in his promiſes,<note n="c." place="margin">Pſal. 50.15 and. 23</note> the right inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon his name, with thankes geuing for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, whereby his true worſhip may be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aryght: which things as he dooth commaund, ſo doth he forbid<note n="d." place="margin">Deut. 4.15</note> all maner of ſuperſtition and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry,<note n="e." place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8 2. Tim. 4.4</note> the contempt &amp; denial of his word,<note n="f." place="margin">Rom. 3.18</note> the
<pb facs="tcp:15228:6"/> lacke of feare,<note place="margin">Iacob. 2.14 1. Iohn. 3.10</note> faith, and loue towards him,<note n="g." place="margin">Apoc. 13.6 &amp; 19.10. &amp; 22.9</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon other creatures, &amp; finally what ſoeuer polluteth his ſeruice, or our conſciences, in whoſe preſence all our doings do appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſayeſt thou of the ſecond: Thou ſhalt not make? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God doth therein declare how he will be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, for ſeeing that his true worſhip<note n="a." place="margin">Deut. 6.13 Rom. 14.23 Matth. 5.16</note> is a worke or ſeruice commaunded in his woord, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of fayth, &amp; tending to his glory: as he is a<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 4.24</note> ſpirit, ſo wil he be worſhipped in ſpirit &amp; truth, without<note n="c." place="margin">Leuit. 18.3</note> any myxture of Idolatry or ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Deut. 7.25 &amp; 12.2. &amp; 14.3</note> And therfore he forbiddeth<note n="d." place="margin">Deut. 4.23 Eſay. 40.18</note> the making of Images, to expreſſe hym by<note n="e." place="margin">Exod. 34.14 Pſalm. 97.7</note> all maner deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or reuerence giuing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either in looking at them, or in bowing the knee before them in prayer: for he is the Lord our God, and wyl not haue his power to be contemned:<note n="f." place="margin">Exod. 34.14 1. Cor. 11.2</note> he is ielous ouer vs, &amp; wyl not ſuffer eyther our ſoules or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes to be defiled with any filthines of Idolatry, which if we doo, he wyll reuenge the ſame to the third &amp; fourth generation. Briefly, he forbiddeth hereby<note n="g." place="margin">Deut. 12.2</note> all repreſentations &amp; tokens of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,<note n="h." place="margin">Eſay. 29.13</note> al ſtraunge worſhip deuiſed by man,<note n="i." place="margin">Apoc. 13.15 and .14.9 and .18.4</note> all Antichriſtian Decrees, and whatſoeuer corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the true ſeruice, &amp; ſpiritual worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:6"/>
            <p>What is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in the third: Thou ſhalt not take? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein the Lord commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth a reuerend vſe of his Name,<note n="a." place="margin">Deut. 6.13</note> truely to ſweare and teſtifie the truth, not<note n="b." place="margin">Iere. 4.1.2</note> only in truth, iudgment, &amp; rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but alſo<note n="c." place="margin">Ioſua. 2.12 2. Cor. 1.23</note> for neceſſities ſake, eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the glory of God, &amp; the ſaluation of our brethren is ſought: requiring alſo herein a faithfull zeale and<note n="d." place="margin">Deut. 6.5 Actes. 2.42</note> loue towardes his word &amp; Sacraments, and what ſoeuer<note n="e." place="margin">1. Cor. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1</note> may ſet forth his glory, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note n="f." place="margin">Deut. 28.58</note> the indiſcret &amp; vnreuerend vſe of his name in vaine &amp; friuolous things, al raſh othes, al<note n="g." place="margin">Pſal. 15.4</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes made for fauor, lucre, and feare, rather than for trial of truth, al<note n="h." place="margin">Leui. 19.12</note> periurie, al othes made<note n="i." place="margin">Deut. 10.21 Ierem. 5.17 Amos. 8.14</note> by Saints, Idols, Meate, or other creatures,<note n="k." place="margin">Deut. 18.10</note> all Coniurations, Sorceries, Charmyngs, Sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayings, witchcraft,<note n="l." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.31</note> curſing &amp; bannyng,<note n="m." place="margin">Ro. 16.17 Apoc. 14.9</note> all falſe doctrines, and corruptions of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and what ſoeuer<note n="n." place="margin">Rom. 2.24</note> cauſeth the name of God to be euyll ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewe the meanyng of the fourth: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that thou keepe holy the Sabboth day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth herein<note n="a." place="margin">Exod. 31.13 Hebr. 4.11</note> the ceaſſyng from bodyly labors &amp; ſinnes, &amp;<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 18.20 Pſalm. 95. Mark. 8.35</note> to meete toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his true feare and loue, to heare, learne, &amp; confeſſe his woord, and<note n="c." place="margin">Coloſ. 3.16</note> to inſtruct one another
<pb facs="tcp:15228:7"/> in the ſame,<note n="d." place="margin">Act. 20.7</note> to communicate at his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, to<note n="e." place="margin">Philip. 4.6</note> render thankes for his benefites, to<note n="f." place="margin">1. Cor. 16.1</note> diſtriubute vnto the neceſſitie of the poore,<note n="g." place="margin">Hebr. 3.13</note> &amp; to meditate our ſpiritual reſt which ſhal be after this lyfe: forbidding likewiſe<note n="h." place="margin">2. Chro. 36.16.</note> the contempt of Eccleſiaſtical meetings, his woord, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the<note n="i." place="margin">Galat. 4.10 Coloſ. 2.16</note> ſuperſtitious obſeruance of dayes &amp; tymes, the folowing of<note n="k." place="margin">Rom. 3.13 Pſal. 119.37</note> paſtymes, gamyng, daunſing, banquetting, and other outward plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, without meditation of heauenly things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the meanyng of the fift Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, Honour thy father and thy moother?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein the Lorde requireth<note n="a." place="margin">Leuit. 20.9 Epheſ. 6.1 Exod. 22.28 Hebr. 13.17</note> humble reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence &amp; loue, not only towardes our natural pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but alſo towards our Magiſtrates, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and maiſters, whom he placeth ouer vs,<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 13.4 1. Pet. 2.14</note> for the benefite of them which doo well, and for the puniſhment of the euyl, requiring our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towardes them,<note n="c." place="margin">Ro. 13.1.14</note> ſo long as they obey his word, from whence whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they decline,<note n="d." place="margin">Daniel. 3.18 Actes. 4.19</note> they are no longer to be obeyed, forbidding alſo<note n="e." place="margin">Leuit. 20.9</note> al diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience &amp; ingratitude of chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards their parents,<note n="f." place="margin">Num. 16. toto 2. Sa. 15. &amp;. 17</note> al contempt and rebellion of ſubiects againſt their magiſtrates, alſo<note n="g." place="margin">Exod. 22.28</note> to blaſpheme them, and to<note n="h." place="margin">1. Reg. 14.16</note> obey them in matters contarry to the truth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What canſt thou ſay of the ſixt, Thou ſhalt not kyll?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 5.23 Iohn. 13.34 Rom. 13.8. Ephe. 4.2.31</note> faithful loue, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, kindneſſe, compaſſion, reconciliation, &amp; mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual embracyng one another in peace, as wel of our enemyes, as of thoſe which loue vs, forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note n="b." place="margin">Gala. 5.20 Epheſ. 4.31 1. Cor. 3.1 and .10.10 Rom. 13.8.9 1. Iohn. 3.10</note> al vnlawfull murder and quarelling out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, al fayned loue, vnmercyfulneſſe, hatred, malice, anger, reproches, tauntes, ſlaundering, murmuring, contentions, deſire of vengeance, &amp; whatſoeuer is repugnant to Chriſtian loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Proceede to the ſeuenth, Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord commaundeth not only<note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 6.15 1. Theſ. 4.4</note> perfecte chaſtitie both in ſoule and body, whether it be in mariage or in ſingle life, that all our partes may be ſanctified vnto him: but alſo he forbiddeth<note n="b." place="margin">Galat. 5.20 Apoc. 21.8</note> al maner of adultry &amp; fornication,<note n="c." place="margin">1. Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſ. 5.5</note> the reſtraining of lawfull mariage in any calling, and the raſhe vowing of ſingle life,<note n="d." place="margin">Math. 5.26 Rom. 6.12 and .7.7</note> vnlawfull luſtes,<note n="e." place="margin">Eſay. 3.16 1. Tim. 2.9 1. Pet. 3.5</note> lyght behauiour, and vnſeemely adorning of the body,<note n="f." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.29 and .5.4 Coloſ 4.6.7 Gal. 5.20.21</note> filthy talke and idle paſtimes, drunkennes min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrelſie, daunſing, &amp; what beſides tendeth to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity and lecherous luſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Declare the eyght, Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein God commaundeth<note n="a." place="margin">Pſal. 15.2 Tit. 2.12 Rom. 13.8</note> rightuouſnes &amp; true dealing in euery calling, &amp; that euery man be content with his owne ſtate, geuing to euery one what of right he ought to haue: forbidding alſo<note n="b." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.28 1. Theſ. 4.6</note> all robbing &amp; faſhood,<note n="c." place="margin">Luk. 12.15 Pſalm. 15.5 Prou. 11.1</note> couetouſnes, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, oppreſſion, bying and ſelling with falſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,<note n="d." place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.10</note> idle liuing,<note n="e." place="margin">Luk. 15.13</note> vnhoneſt waſting of goods or ſubſtance, &amp; what els doth ſauour of deceyt, the ſame is ſtealing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewe the ſenſe and meanyng of the Ninth, Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth herein<note n="a." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.25 1. Sam. 33 15</note> in court &amp; iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; in al our wordes &amp; couenaunts, that truth may floriſh, to ſaue our neighbors harmles,<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 1.16 1. Sam. 10.1</note> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wrong iudgment, or any reſpect of perſons therin, the making of wicked Lawes &amp; decrees, alſo<note n="c." place="margin">Deut. 19.16 Epheſ. 4.25 1. Cor. 13. toto</note> falſe witnes, and lying tales, flattery, ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions, falſe accuſations, and what ſo euer em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payreth the good name of our brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſayſt thou of the laſt, Thou ſhalt not couet?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this the Lord commaundeth<note n="a." place="margin">Deut. 6.5 Math. 22.37 Luk. 10.27</note> the whole
<pb facs="tcp:15228:8"/> harte to be poſſeſſed with loue, that what ſoeuer man doth wiſh or deſyre, it may be free from luſt &amp; corrupt affection, &amp; ſerue to the glory of God, and profit of his neighbours, forbidding hereby<note n="b." place="margin">Geneſ. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Math. 5.28 Rom. 6.12</note> al wicked thoughts &amp; vnlawful deſires both of ſoule &amp; body, although our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent be not therto,<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.22</note> al corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of original ſinne by Adam, al lack of grace, and what ſoeuer wanteth of the integritie &amp; perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherin man was made. By al which precepts, it may appere, that<note n="d." place="margin">Iob. 15.14 Deut. 27.26 Leuit. 18.5 Luk. 17.10</note> nothing but true rightuouſnes and innocencie can pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that thou art not able of thy ſelf,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.3</note> becauſe of thy ſins, to fulfil theſe lawes, why therfore did God commaund that, which thou canſt not do?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, hereby he declareth how that his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in me,<note n="a." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.23 24.</note> is corrupted with ſin, for nothing is here required, which I could not haue done before my fal in Adam. Secondly<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 27.26</note> here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded which I am not bound to do. Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Deut. 6.25</note> he doth not reſpect what I of my ſelf cand do, but what his iuſtice doth require. Laſt of al it ſetteth forth the<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 4.15 and .7.7</note> wrath of God, &amp; bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth me to the feelyng of my ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why God is mercyful to thouſands, &amp; wil not
<pb facs="tcp:15228:9"/> ſurely puniſh ſinne ſo ſharply as thou thinkeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Exo. 20.6</note>God in deede is mercyfull to them that loue hym, &amp; truly repent, but he is a<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 7.69 and .11.7. Deut. 32.35.</note> iuſt Iudge, &amp; a God of ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance to puniſh the wickednes of the vngodly, which breake his commaundementes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this I gather, that many are in a woful caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concernyng the wicked, which be voyde of fayth, &amp; of the mercy of God,<note n="a." place="margin">1. Ti. 1.9. Deut. 27.26.</note> the curſe of the law hangeth vpon them. But touching the elect, of which company I am perſwaded that I am one:<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn. 3.16. 2. Cor. 5.21. Rom. 3.25</note> Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, in myne own nature hath ſuffred to deliuer me from ſinne &amp; the puniſhments therof, &amp; hath brought me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fauor of God againe, of which benefite I lay holde<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 1.16. Act. 15.11</note> with a true fayth,<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 10.17</note> which commeth by the preaching of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> doctrine of faith,<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 11.28 Iohn. 5.24</note> conteynyng the promiſes of God vnto ſaluation,<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 24.47 Iohn. 3.15 and 6.47</note> to all whiche truely repent, and lay hold of Chriſtes merites by a ſure truſt in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What do the promiſes of the Goſpel meane?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt they teach me that the law of God is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled for me, by Chriſt,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 5.19 Ephe. 2.15 Galat. 3.13</note> by whom I haue my ſins forgiuen, &amp; with<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30. 2. Cor. 5.21</note> whoſe ryghtuouſnes I am clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, &amp; may now boldly ſtand before the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeat of God. Secondly, that my ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.24 &amp; 4.5.16</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth onely of the free mercy of God, without my merites or good deedes. Thirdly<note n="d." place="margin">Mat. 22.14 2. Cor. 4.6</note> although they be offred to all, yet they take effect in none to ſaluation, but onely in the electe, whoſe harts God lighteneth with fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shew me what fayth is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a kind of faith, called<note n="a." place="margin">Iames. 2.14 Actes. 8.13</note> a dead faith, beleuing the word of God to be true, &amp; al things therein conteyned, and goeth no further: but the true faith is<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 17.3</note> the faire knowledge of the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good will and mercy of God ſhewed towards man in Chriſt, &amp;<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17</note> a ſure truſt in the ſame, which<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 6. toto</note> in due time bringeth forth the fruites of good liuing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doeſt thou learne hereby?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt I learne to know God, who is made<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.16</note> my father by Chriſt, thorow adoption and grace.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly,<note n="b." place="margin">Galat. 2.20</note> I apply to my ſelfe by this my fayth, al the merits of Chriſt as fully as if I had
<pb facs="tcp:15228:11"/> done the ſame my ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 4.19 Hebr. 4.16 and. 10.22</note> I haue a ſure truſt in his merits and mercy, &amp; boldnes to offer vp my prayers to God the father by him.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſt of all I knowe his promiſes to<note n="d." place="margin">Hebr. 11.1</note> be faithfull &amp; true, and that he will performe them, when it pleaſeth his godly wiſdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence commeth fayth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the gifte<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 11.25 27. &amp;. 13.11 Actes. 16.14 Rom. 12.6 Galat. 5.22 Epheſ. 2.8</note> of God, wrought in my hart by the preaching of the Goſpel, and by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the ſumme of the fayth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue in God the father almighty, maker of heauen and earth, and in Ieſus Chriſt his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne our Lord, which was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the virgin Mary, ſuffred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pontius Pilate, was crucified, dead, &amp; buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he deſcended into hel, and roſe again the third day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, he aſcended into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſitteth on the ryght hand of God the father almighty, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence ſhall he come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt, the holy catholike church, the communion of ſaintes, the forgeuenes of ſins, the reſurrection of the body, &amp; the life euerlaſting.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What art thou taught hereby?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> Firſt, what to beleeue of God my father &amp; creatour.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Secondly, of Chriſt my redeemer. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the holy ghoſt my ſanctifier. Laſt of all, concerning the church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What canſt thou ſay of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 4.24</note> a ſpiritual nature<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 16.26</note> euerlaſting<note n="c." place="margin">1. Sam. 45 5.6.7</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,<note n="d." place="margin">Pſalm. 139 7.8.9</note> infinite,<note n="e." place="margin">Pſal. 119.137</note> true,<note n="f." place="margin">Math. 19.17</note> good,<note n="g." place="margin">Pſal. 11.7</note> righteous, and<note n="h." place="margin">Exod. 34.6</note> mercifull,<note n="i." place="margin">Geneſ. 1.1</note> who hath made the world, &amp;<note n="k." place="margin">Iohn. 1.1</note> hath begotten the ſonne of him ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>The ſonne is<note n="l." place="margin">Prou. 8.23 Hebr. 1.3 Apocal. 1.8</note> wiſedome &amp; image of the father, begotten of the father, very God of very God,<note n="m." place="margin">Iohn. 1.14 Galat. 4.4</note> who in his tyme appoynted, became man.</p>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt is<note n="n." place="margin">Ioh. 14.16.26</note> the power &amp; vertue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from them both: which three, although they be<note n="o." place="margin">Mat. 3.16.17</note> diſtinct in perſons, yet are they<note n="p." place="margin">Deut. 6.4 Iohn. 1.1. and 5.18.21 1. Iohn. 5.7</note> equall and al one in Godhead, eternitie, dignitie, and power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſaiſt thou of the firſt part of this faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue that God is not only the<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 3.17 Rom. 8.16</note> natural father of his ſonne Chriſt, but alſo that he is by grace my father, by whoſe wiſedome as heauen
<pb facs="tcp:15228:12"/> and earth and all things therin conteyned, were made, ſo the ſame by his<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 145.15 Hebr. 1.3 Mat. 10.29</note> power is gouerned &amp; preſerued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What thinkeſt thou of the ſecond?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleue that<note n="a." place="margin">Hebr. 4.15</note> the ſonne of God became man, in al things lyke vnto me, onely ſyn excepted, &amp; in my nature wrought what was needfull to my ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="b." place="margin">Math. 1.21 Actes. 4.12</note> wherefore he is named Ieſus, that is, a ſaueour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is thy ſaluation wrought?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word Chriſt, doth teach the ſame, for firſt it ſignifieth him to be a king, &amp; to haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed to him ſelfe<note n="a." place="margin">Act. 20.28 Luk. 1.33</note> by his blood, the ſpirituall kingdome of his church,<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 8.36 1. Iohn. 3.5 1. Ioſ. 13.14 1. Cor. 15.55</note> all the enemies therof co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered. Which kingdome now he gouerneth<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13 1. Cor. 6.19</note> by his word, and by his ſpirit, wherby he raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in my hart, and in the harts of his elect.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it teacheth that he was a<note n="d." place="margin">Hebr. 5.56.7</note> prieſt to offer vp him ſelf once for al a ſweet ſacrifice, to take away my ſins, &amp; to be a<note n="e." place="margin">Iohn. 14.13 Rom. 8.34</note> mediator, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in whoſe name I maye offer vp my prayers to God my heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, &amp; through him be heard.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it putteth me in minde that he was<note n="f." place="margin">Act. 3.21</note> a Prophet, ſent to preach the wil of his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, whom<note n="g." place="margin">Math. 17.5</note> alone I muſt heare and obey, as my Lord, who being thus appoynted of his
<pb facs="tcp:15228:12"/> father,<note n="h." place="margin">Mark. 14.10 &amp; 15.15.24 Ioh. 19.38</note> was betraied of Iudas, condemned by Pilat, crucified by the Iewes, buried by Ioſeph of Aromathia, and Nicodemus, ſuffred<note n="i." place="margin">Eſay. 53.4 Coloſ. 1.22</note> in his body, not onely the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts due to my body, but alſo<note n="k." place="margin">Mat. 27.46</note> in his ſoule the puniſhments due to my ſoule, that was, the very torments of hel, &amp; death, and ſeparation from God,<note n="l." place="margin">Rom. 5.19 Coloſ. 2.14 1. Iohn. 3.8 Apoc. 20.14</note> by whoſe death my obedience is wrought, the malediction of Gods law cancelled, the diuel, &amp; al his power ſubdued, the wrath of God appeaſed, and I ſet in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor agayne. And thus is the death of Chriſt, the onely and full raunſome for my ſins, by vertue whereof, ſin alſo dyeth, and is killed in me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſayſt thou of his reſurrection?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 4.25</note> As he dyed for my ſins, ſo he roſe agayne for my iuſtification,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.8</note> hauing gotten the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ouer ſin, death, hel, and damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; geueth me power through his ſpirit<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 8.10.11</note> to riſe vnto newe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of lyfe, aſſuring me, that my bodily death ſhalbe no deſtruction, but I ſhall ryſe againe at the laſt day, to lyfe euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shew thy mynd of his aſcenſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He aſcended<note n="a." place="margin">Actes. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and. 3.21 Math. 28 18.20</note> with his body into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where he remayneth, hauing al power giuen him of his
<pb facs="tcp:15228:13"/> father, but with his ſpirit he is preſent with his people:<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 14.2 Titus. 2.5 Coloſ. 3.1.2</note> by which his aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion for me in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where he alſo continueth a mediator to make interceſſion for me to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; finally teacheth me to ſet myne affection vppon heauenly things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What meaneſt thou by his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue that he which is my ſaueour<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 24.31 2. Theſ. 1.8.10 Luk. 21.35</note> ſhall come to cleare me and al his elect in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; to condemne the wicked, which in their lyfe tyme refuſed him, to folow their pleaſures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſaieſt thou of the holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue that<note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 6.11</note> he is the ſpirit of ſanctification,<note n="b." place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6</note> geuen to lighten my mynde,<note n="c." place="margin">Iohn. 16.13</note> &amp; to lead me into all truth, he is<note n="d." place="margin">2. Cor. 1.22</note> the earneſt of myne inheritance in heauen,<note n="e." place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13</note> the ſeale to imprinte Gods promiſes in my hart<note n="f." place="margin">Iohn. 7.36 Eſay. 55.1</note> the fountayne of grace, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which purgeth mee from myne vncleannes, and<note n="g." place="margin">Ro. 8.10.11</note> maketh me to dye to ſin, &amp; to be holy vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shew thy mynde concerning the church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The church is<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.29 Epheſ. 1.4 10.11</note> the ſocietie of al faithful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom God in Chriſt hath choſen to ſaluation
<pb facs="tcp:15228:13"/> before the world was made, of<note n="b." place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.21</note> which number I beleeue that I am one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What be the markes thereof?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 8.47 and. 10.27</note>The ſincere word of God,<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 28.19</note> the right admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the ſacraments,<note n="c." place="margin">Math. 18.17. 1. Cor. 5.1.</note> &amp; eccleſiaſticall diſcipline.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why is the church called holy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe God wil haue his people to liue<note n="a." place="margin">Titus. 2.12</note> holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſoberly, &amp; rightuouſly in this world, &amp; not<note n="b." place="margin">Ephe. 4.30</note> to greue the holy ghoſt by any vncleannes, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be ſanctified, &amp; by whom whileſt they ſuffer themſelues to be led, they<note n="c." place="margin">Iohn. 16.13</note> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not erre in matters of fayth and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What meaneth the Communion of Saintes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſignifieth<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 12.5 1. Cor. 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the felowſhip which al the elect haue one with another,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Pet. 4.10 Galat. 6.2</note> communicating accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of fayth, al ſpiritual graces amongeſt themſelues,<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3</note> ſtudying to keepe the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the ſpirit in the bonde of peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What beleeueſt thou of the forgiuenes of ſins?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I beleeue that before my ſins be forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:15228:14"/> me,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 5.8.10 Epheſ. 2.1.2 1. Cor. 6.11</note> there is nothing in me but mere wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. Secondly I beleeue that al my ſins, &amp; the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therof be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away<note n="b." place="margin">1. Pet. 2.4 Eſay. 53.5 1. Cor. 1.30 2. Cor. 5.21</note> by Chriſts death, and I made partaker of his rightuouſnes. Thirdly, I beleeue<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.25</note> that fayth alone, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthines of my ſelf, doth make me partaker of theſe graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſayſt thou of the reſt, the reſurrection of the body, and life euerlaſting?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue when this lyfe is ended, that<note n="a." place="margin">Eccle. 12.7 Apoc. 14.13 Luk. 16.22 Philip. 1.23</note> my ſoule ſhall go to God, &amp; my body reſt in the earth to the laſt day, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhall both ioyne togither againe<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 15.53</note> incorruptible, and remayne with God for euer in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can ſuch a faith as this be fruitleſſe, &amp; without good workes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, but good workes do folow fayth, as the<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 7.17 Iames. 2.24 1. Pet. 1.12</note> teſtimonies and fruites of my thankfulneſſe to God, wherby my fayth is known, and approued by men:<note n="b." place="margin">Galat. 5.6</note> wherfore it is called a fayth which worketh by loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What workes muſt thou do?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such as be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded me in the<note n="a." place="margin">Matth. 19 17.18</note> law of God,
<pb facs="tcp:15228:14"/> 
               <note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 1.8 Epheſ. 2.10</note> which as they come of grace geuen me, &amp; not of mine owne power, ſo muſt they needs be done: for firſt<note n="c." place="margin">1. Pet. 1.16</note> God hath ſo commaunded. Secondly, his<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 6. toto Titus. 2.14</note> benefits bynde me thereto. Thirdly,<note n="e." place="margin">Coloſ. 2.12</note> my baptiſme doth teach me to dye vnto ſin, and liue vnto rightuouſnes. Fourthly,<note n="f." place="margin">Mat. 5.36 1. Pet. 2.12</note> I muſt gloryfy god by my wel doing. Laſt of all,<note n="g." place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10</note> I muſt make ſtrong my faith and election, &amp; learne to auoyde the wrath of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What rewarde ſhalt thou haue for thy good deedes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The workes which I do before I be iuſtified before God by Chriſt,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 14.23 Hebr. 11.6 Iohn. 3.26</note> cannot pleaſe him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be done without faith. The workes which folow my regeneration,<note n="b." place="margin">Apoc. 7.14 Math. 25.40 Luk. 17.10 1. Cor. 15.58</note> do pleaſe God, not becauſe of any worthines of mine in them, but God accepteth them, becauſe of my fayth in Chriſt, through whom they are not don in vaine, ſo that the reward which is giuen vnto them, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth onely of<note n="c." place="margin">Apocal. 22</note> the free mercy &amp; fauour of God, whileſt he rewardeth not my deſerts, but crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his giftes of grace in me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With what helpes doth God further thee to ſaluation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides that the word of God<note n="a." place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.3</note> doth help to
<pb facs="tcp:15228:15"/> vphold my fayth,<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 28.19 1. Cor. 11.23 Gene. 11.11</note> the ſacraments &amp; prayer are alſo helpes to me, for by them the Lord helpeth myne infirmitie, by outward ſignes repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to mee ſpirituall graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do the ſacraments ſerue thee to any other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ſerue not onely to<note n="a." place="margin">Exod. 12.11 12.13 Math. 26.26 and .27.19 1. Cor. 11.26 1. Cor. 11.17 Exod. 42.43 1. Sam. 7.26</note> teach me heauenly thyngs, but alſo to kyndle a deſyre of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in my hart, to ſtyrre me vp to thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for my redemption, to knyt me in loue with the godly, and as markes of Religion to teſtifie how I differ from the Heathen &amp; wicked: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſuch as refuſe to vſe the ſame,<note n="b." place="margin">Mark. 8.38 Luk. 14.18 24</note> do not only deny God, but are alſo arrogant and proud.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is a Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an holy ſigne, inſtituted of<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 21.25 Iohn. 3.5 Actes. 2.38 Rom. 4.11</note> God, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme my fayth, and to ſeale in my hart the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Gods mercy towardes me for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of my ſins and ſaluation in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether do the ſacraments giue grace to the receiuer or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They<note n="a." place="margin">Actes. 2.38</note> neither of themſelues nor in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:15228:15"/> includ or giue grace, for that is the gift of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, but they be holy ſignes, whereby, as by an inſtrument, God dooth worke and ſeale grace in my hart by fayth receyued, and yet they be not bare or naked ſignes, but grace is truely preſent to my fayth, when I receyue the ſame aryght.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many Sacraments be there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two, the one is Baptiſme, wherwith I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued into Chriſtes church. The other is the Supper of the Lord, wherwith I am nouriſhed in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is Baptiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wherin as water waſheth away the filthines of my body, ſo<note n="a." place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21</note> the blood of Chriſt ſprinkled vpon my ſoule, by the hand of fayth, waſheth away my ſins, and the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wherby<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 6.5</note> I am incorporate into his body, &amp; made partaker of his benefits, to dye vnto ſin, &amp; to liue vnto rightuouſnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why are children to be baptiſed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe by<note n="a." place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3 Rom. 5.12 Actes. 2.39 Geneſ. 17.7</note> nature they be the children of wrath by Adams ſin, to whom alſo the promiſe
<pb facs="tcp:15228:16"/> of Gods free mercy and fauour reacheth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the Lords ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 26.26</note>It is the ſacrament of my redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the death of Chriſt, wherin by the miſticall recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of bread and wyne, through a true fayth, I am made<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16 Luk. 22.19 Iohn. 6.51</note> partaker of al the benefits of Chriſts paſſion, for as bread broken doth feede &amp; nouriſh my body, &amp; wine refreſh my hart, ſo the<note n="c." place="margin">Luk. 22.19 Iohn. 6.51</note> body of Chriſt was torne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, &amp; his blud ſhed, to waſh away my ſins, and to feed &amp; refreſh my ſoule to lyfe euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether is the bread chaunged into the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body of Chriſt, or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sacraments of bread and wyne<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 26.29 Iohn. 6.51 53.5. 1. Cor. 10.16.17. and 11.24</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill in their former nature and ſubſtance, neuertheleſſe there is a great chaunge, for thoſe things which before were but as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon meats, are now made the Sacraments or holy ſignes of Chriſtes body and blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How doſt thou eat Chriſts body, or drinke his blood?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 6.35</note>Spiritually, and by grace, whileſt I beleeue
<pb facs="tcp:15228:16"/> that he dyed for my ſins,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.24</note> and roſe agayne for my iuſtification, for it is fayth that maketh me par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of his benefits &amp; goodnes which are ſealed to me by his Sacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do all men which receyue this ſacrament, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the ſpirituall grace alyke?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As in Baptiſme none<note n="a." place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21 Actes. 2.38 and .8.18. Mark. 16.16</note> but the faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 11 28.29</note> of their ſins, ſo in the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, none but ſuch are partakers of the grace, and benefits of Chriſtes death. The wicked in deed receyue the outward elements of bread and wine, but becauſe they lacke true fayth, they are not partakers of the ſpiritual grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How muſt thou frame thy ſelfe to receyue this ſacrament worthily?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt I muſt<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 26.75 Ierem. 24.7 Ioel. 2.12.13 Rom. 6. toto</note> conſider the greeuouſnes of my ſins, &amp; from my hart vnfaynedly hate and deteſt the ſame, &amp; euer after giue my ſelfe to godlines &amp; vertue. Secondly,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28. &amp;. 2. Cor. 13.5</note> I muſt try and examin my ſelfe whether I haue a true fayth in the promiſes of Chriſt. Thirdly<note n="c." place="margin">Matth. 5.24 and. 22.39</note> I muſt reconcile my ſelfe to all men, and continue in Chriſtian loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:17"/>
            <p>Now remayneth the other helpe giuen thee of God, that is to ſay, prayer: tel me what it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prayer is the<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 6.6 Iohn. 16.23 1. Tim. 2.8</note> lifting vp of my hart to God, and the aſking in Chriſts name, of things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me and the whole church,<note n="b." place="margin">Philip. 4.6 Coloſ. 4.2</note> with thankes geuing for his benefits, and goodnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To whom muſt thou pray?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To<note n="a." place="margin">Pſal. 50.15 Iohn. 16.33</note> God alone, firſt, becauſe I<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 10.14</note> beleeue in him alone. Secondly, he alone<note n="c." place="margin">1. Reg. 8.39</note> knoweth my hart: thirdly<note n="d." place="margin">Eſay. 40.8</note> he wil not giue his glory to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; therfore I am forbidden to pray to ſaints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How canſt thou which art a ſinner, pray to God which hateth ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 14.13.14 and. 16.23 Actes. 4.12 1. Ti. 2.5.6 1. Iohn. 2.2</note>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray not in truſt of myne own rightuouſnes, but in the name of Chriſt, who is the<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 14.6</note> way for me to come to the father, who<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 8.34 1. Tim. 2.5.6 1. Iohn. 13 Iohn. 13.24</note> continueth my mediatour at the right hand of the father, <hi>d</hi> who loueth, &amp; hath<note n="e." place="margin">Coloſ. 1.22</note> reconciled me to the father,<note n="f." place="margin">Math. 3.17</note> &amp; in whom the father is wel pleaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For whom muſt thou pray?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all men liuing, for<note n="a." place="margin">1. Ti. 2.1.2 Matth. 5.44 Luk. 6.27</note> kings, magiſtrates,
<pb facs="tcp:15228:17"/> miniſters, yea, and for my enemies: but for the dead I haue no commaundement to pray, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I help them after they be gon hence, for as they be found at the day of their death, ſo ſhal they ryſe agayne, onely this I can doo, to giue God thankes for their deliuerance out of this world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How muſt thou prepare thy ſelfe to pray?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I muſt<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.26 1. Iohn. 5.14</note> be touched with the neceſſity of thoſe whome I pray for,<note n="b." place="margin">Matth. 6.7</note> my mynd muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout, and not caried to &amp; fro with vayn thoughts. I muſt appere before God<note n="c." place="margin">Pſal. 51.17 Iacob. 1.6</note> in true repentance and fayth,<note n="d." place="margin">Math. 5.23</note> being at loue with al men,<note n="e." place="margin">Eſay. 1.18 and. 59.2</note> framing my life ryghtuouſly,<note n="f." place="margin">1. Iohn. 5.14 1. Cor. 14. toto</note> aſking in ſuch a tongue as I vnderſtand, according to the will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How muſt thou pray?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to the forme preſcribed of our ſauior Chriſt, in theſe wordes, Our father which art in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, halowed be thy name. Thi kingdom come. Thy wil be done in earth as it is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Geue vs this day our dayly bread. And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe agaynſt vs. And leade vs not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but deliuer vs from euill. For thyne is the
<pb facs="tcp:15228:18"/> kingdome, the power, and the glory, for euer. So be it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the meaning of this prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We pray to God in the firſt petition, that<note n="a." place="margin">Pſal. 89.5.6 1. Cor. 10.31 Ioſua. 24.14 15</note> his glory may appeare, and that<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 2.24</note> our liues &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation may ſet forth the ſame. In the ſecond, we pray that God would<note n="c." place="margin">Iohn. 16.13 Ro. 8.10.11</note> gouerne the kingdom of his church, killing ſin, and the luſts thereof in the ſame, and to renue it to rightuouſnes of lyfe. That he would alſo<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 16.20 1. Iohn. 3.8</note> tread downe Satan and al his power, and that he would ſhortly<note n="e." place="margin">Apo. 22.20</note> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the number of his elect, &amp; haſten the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt to iudgement. In the third we pray,<note n="f." place="margin">Luk. 22.42</note> that al our doings may be agreable to his will, without contradiction or murmuring. In the fourth, we deſire him<note n="g." place="margin">Pſalm. 14.1 15</note> to grant vs whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is needful to the ſuſtenance and preſeruation of our life, and that all our doings may be to his glory, and the profit af our neyghbours. In the fift we pray<note n="h." place="margin">Pſal. 51.9 1. Iohn. 2.12 and. 18.35 Math. 5.45</note> for the forgiuenes of our ſins &amp; the puniſhment thereof, for his mercyes ſake, euen as we ſhal pardone others their offences done to vs, without bearing malice or hatred towardes them.</p>
            <p>In the laſt we pray that God<note n="i." place="margin">Epheſ. 6.10 Rom. 16.20</note> would guyde vs with his ſpirit, that we may get the victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Sathan, ſin, and hel, &amp; be defended from all
<pb facs="tcp:15228:9"/> euyll. After we conclude with theſe wordes: For thyne is the kingdome. &amp;c. to ſet forth our deſire to his glory, his honour, &amp; prayſe, whoſe power is alſo infinit, and therfore he can graunt our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes.<note n="k." place="margin">Rom. 11.36 Act. 4.9.11 Pſal. 114.7 1. Chro. 29 10.</note> We end with this word, Amen, both deſiring that what we haue aſked, maye be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and alſo aſſuring our ſelues, that our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes ſhall be fulfilled accordingly as they be agreeyng to the wil of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there any helpe for thee, to praye more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea truely,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.11 Actes. 13.3</note> faſting is a ſpecial preparatiue to the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is a Chriſtian faſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not onely an<note n="a." place="margin">Eſay. 58.3 Ioel. 2.12. Pſal. 35.13 Zachar. 7.5</note> abſtinence from meats, and drynkes, to chaſtice my body, but alſo from ſin and the delights thereof, which hurt the ſoule, to the end through true repentance, fayth, Godly prayer, and renouncing of euill, the Spirit may haue dominion in me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the right vſe of faſting?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 9.27</note>Firſt to chaſtice my body, and to bring it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:15228:10"/> ſubiection to the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b." place="margin">Ioel. 2.12</note>Secondly, to be a witnes of my true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and ſubmiſſion to the will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="c." place="margin">Math. 26.41</note>Thirdly, that my ſpirit may be more ready to prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there any abuſe in the exerciſe of faſting?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, many,<note n="a." place="margin">Eſay. 58.3 Zachar. 7.5</note> firſt to faſt longer then the body may indure, and after to fare deliciouſly. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,<note n="b." place="margin">Coloſ. 2.16 Galat. 4.10 1. Tim. 4.3</note> to put holines in faſting one day more than another, or in abſteyning from one meate more than from an other. Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Eſay. 58.3 Rom. 3.24</note> to thinke by faſting to purchaſe forgiuenes of ſins, wheras the ſame commeth only of the free mercy of God in Chriſt, without any mans worthines or deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. Laſt of all, in abſteyning from meates, not to<note n="d." place="margin">Galat. 5.24 Titus. 2.12</note> abſtayne from ſins, and all things which cauſe or nouriſh the ſame: for ſince the lyfe of man ought to be a meditation of godlynes, this ought to be the indeuour of the faythfull, to lyue godly, ſoberly, and ryghtuouſly in this world, wayting for the bleſſed appearance of Ieſus Chriſt their only ſauiour and redeemer. To whom with the father, and the holy Ghoſt, three diſtinct perſons, and one eternall God, be al laud and prayſe, for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15228:18"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London,</hi> nygh vnto the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas <hi>Dawſon, and Thomas Gardyner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  <p>T. D.</p>
                  <p> T. G.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
